Guide to the Ronald R. Spadafora Papers 1911-2018 (bulk, 1970s-2010s) MS 3134
New-York Historical Society
- Education. Specifics (Fire Department High School). Personal. Reference., circa 2000s (Offsite-box 9760)
  All appears to relate to training of some form for fire departments. Lots on FOMI (i.e. FDNY Officers Management Institute). Envelope with several certifications awarded Spadafora for courses completed. Folders, binders, loose docs on various specific courses or related (e.g. grants to do training; MA in homeland security offered by Naval Postgrad School; binder of presentation slides on "Delivering High Impact Instruction" by Leadership Research Institute, etc). Loose doc/emails re: Fire Department High School. A packet of materials re: diversity in the workplace training, specific context being FDNY's minority hiring issues (a DVD "Firehouse" movie on Black/white theme is in the box). Some is related to FD efforts at public training: binder on Fire Safety education. (Includes digital formats)
- Policies & Procedures. Personal. Reference., circa 1990s-2004 (Offsite-box 9877)
  This box holds a set of folders that appear to be Spadafora's office files from circa 2003-04 when he was an Assistant Bureau Chief in the Bureau of Fire Prevention, though the files hold a few documents back to the 1990s. The files include a mix of technical topics, such as carbon monoxide, fire extinguishers, sprinklers, FDNY fire prevention reference guide (2001), etc. (with tearsheets, vendor product info, and other reference material); administrative matters, such as budgeting and revenue, attendance control, objectives, time use analyses; and specific FDNY fire prevention issues, such as fire safety plans for 171 West 85th Street and Pier 86, proposed rules on storage of compressed gas, and others. In a file on union District Council 37 is a copy of the union's laudatory comments about Spadafora, sent to Commissioner Scoppetta urging Spadafora be named to the vacant Chief position (March 2004). VHS from vendor Mobile Hi-Fog re: fire suppression equipment. Photos/snapshots of docked freighters (mostly), with an emphasis on one named "Independence" (2003). (Includes video format)
- Policies & Procedures. Education., circa 1979-1990s (Offsite-box 7438)
  Binder: CWD (City Wide Drills) 1-13, includes the baseline manual (for training) issued in 1983, with subsequent notices of revokes, annotations, tearsheets and other related inserts through the 1990s. Binder of Firefighting procedures manual, issued circa 1979, marked as outdated; includes usual tearsheets and other related inserts through 1990s. Binder of firefighting procedures: Ladder Company Operations, issued 1983, marked as outdated, with inserts, etc into 1990s.
- Policies & Procedures. Education., circa 1980s-2000s (Offsite-box 9821)
  5 binders: 1) Labeled "AUC (All Unit Circulars)-250" includes policy & procedure memos (equipment use, roles of police vs fire depts, etc.), etc from 1980s-90s, again with tearsheets and other inserts to circa 1997, heavily annotated. 2) Labeled "Chief Course" includes "fire tech" promotion course material (1999-2000). 3) Labeled "Battalion Chief Promotion Course" includes test prep/fire tech (1989). 4) Labeled "Lieutenant's Exams, 1986, 1992 (sample test), 1992, 1997": content is as labeled and is a standard package of test prep materials distributed by FDNY as "Previous Lieutenants Exams". 5) Unlabeled binder but appears to have material related to lieutenant promotion course (1997); some lists at front of people promoted or eligible to be promoted (circa 1999).
- Policies & Procedures. Education., circa 1968-2000s (Offsite-box 9822)
  Binder labeled AUC 200-1 (All Unit Circulars) with policies, procedures, notices (technical and administrative), and inserted fire tech tests, 1990s. Binder labeled "outdated" with tearsheets, fire tech tests, AUCs. Binder of Fire Tech "Captain's Course", mostly from 2006, with a few at back from 1999-2002. Binder of Fire Tech courses for Firefighting Seminar and for Battalion Chief Course, 2003. Binder of Battalion Chiefs Incident Command Course, which includes various AUCs, bulletins, manuals (marine), etc. Print matter: FDNY Operational reference book (2nd ed., 4th ed., 5th ed, 8th ed), Housing Maintenance Code 1968.
- Policies & Procedures. Education. Reference., circa 2000s (Offsite-box 9806)
  Print matter: FDNY Strategic Plan 2007-08 and related midterm report, FDNY Risk Management Plan 2004-05, FDNY Medal Day 2007, FDNY annual reports 2003-07, FDNY Runs & Workers 2005-07, FDNY Factory Inspection manual, FDNY high rise safety seminar and related, FDNY fire safety seminar for residential superintendents. General books not specific to FDNY: Fire Protection Handbook (14th ed) with lots of fire tech promotion course inserts from Spadafora, and 16th ed; and other texts on fire protection, fire safety, and fire insurance, some pamphlets on fire safety. DVD of FDNY humanitarian awards 2007. (Includes digital formats)
- Policies & Procedures. Education. Reference., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9250)
  FDNY Chief Officer Quick Guide Under River Rail Operations, 2008. Binder re: procedures for collapses, lofts, under river rail. CDs/DVDs from FDNY for training (natural gas) and guides (forcible entry, operational P&P), "PC data backup 2011". Binder "Evolutions": FDNY procedures re: pumping, hoses, water, ladders, etc. Tearsheets etc re: "Engine Operations". Material on fireproof tenement houses, high rises, multiple dwellings. Forcible entry reference guide. Binder: "Command and Control Procedures". Binder: "Operational Procedures at Emergencies" (steam, natural gas, water). (Includes digital formats)
- Policies & Procedures. Education. Reference., circa 1980s-2000s (Offsite-box 9548)
  Binder: FDNY "Fire Protection Inspector Training", 2004, used for 2005 course. Binder of Fire Prevention-related procedures, laws, etc., circa 2002. Binder of AIA (American Insurance Association) Special Interest Bulletins, with index 1940s-1980. Binder re: AUC 147 (Fire Prevention Inspections), 1980s-90s. Binder re: ABR(?), re: procedures/training for fire safety for schools with students with physical disabilities, 1989. 2 books: "Au Coeur du devouement" and Fire Protection Handbook. (See also box 9898)
- Policies & Procedures. Education. Reference., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9745)
  Materials on emergency action plans (EAP): "EAPD On-Site Exam Format" (study materials); Annotated copy of chapters from print matter re: medical care & like; first aid book; photocopies of web articles, Homeland Security bulletins, memos, and other reference material on bombings and other emergencies; binder of Safety Coordinator Course material. Also thick folder and floppy on ARCS (NYC's Auxiliary Radio Communications System); lots of Chapter 13 of Communications Manual, with annotations. (Includes digital formats)
- Policies & Procedures. Education. Reference., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9787)
  2 binders of training material on incident management; looks like a core set of Powerpoint presentation & other related material, with various inserts from South Africa, wildfires, and FDNY's Incident Management Plan for New Year's Eve at Times Square, 12/31/2008. Various textbooks on fires and firefighting. NYS student manuals on rope rescue and on rescue heavy rigging operations. An FDNY Special Operations Command FEMA Manual (2007). 2 DVDs related to South Africa. 2 books on leadership. (Includes digital formats)
- Policies & Procedures. Education. Reference., circa 2004-12 (Offsite-box 9792)
  Files of reference material, circa 2004-12, some used for an article in WNYF on communications/cell towers, most perhaps used as research & reference for Spadafora's Fire Science course (FIS 101) at John Jay/CUNY. 2007 course syllabus (text is Introduction to Fire Protection by Robert Klinoff and the course is structured around the chapters, which include administrative matters, building codes, and technical matters (equipment, fire protection, prevention, chemistry/physics); many Spadafora files refer to chapters and likely tie to these). Files hold tearsheets, presentations, product materials, webpages, FDNY policies & procedures, etc. Primary topics are communications (cell towers, radios, wi-fi, interoperability, FD Operations Command-FDOC, etc.), Compressed Air Foam Systems (CAFS), and explosion protection (dust, sugar dust). Some material relates to WTC in connection with the technical topics. Lots of CDs with product info and other matter. (Includes digital formats)
- Policies & Procedures. Education. Reference., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9804)
  Folders of print matter on various technical matters, appears to relate to Spadafora's Fire Science course at John Jay, 2000s. Tearsheets, FDNY procedures, webpages, WNYFs, product brochures, CDs/DVDs. Subjects: Foam, fire suppression, barricade/fireblocking gel, fire/ice, fire boats (including FDNY Marine Operations Strategy Manual, 2010), lightweight construction (including several copies of FDNY, Division 6's "Lightweight Residential One to Four Family Homes: Construction Features, Tactical Considerations, and Operational Procedures"), MRI/magnetic field fire extinguishers. (Includes digital formats)
- Policies & Procedures. Education. Reference., circa 1980s-2013 (Offsite-box 9837)
  3 non-commercial videocassettes (Social Club Task Force Inspection tape, 2 of FDNY videos: fire prevention series). Book "Under Fire: The West is Burning" re: western wildfires and other docs on wildfires, including binder of Incident Command System print matter from National Wildfire Coordinating Group (1980s). FDNY binder: "Combating Terrorism Leadership Program", 2004. Various presentations/print matter on incident management, emergency management, including chemical/LNG. Operational security plan (2005). EDC's "Industrial Strategy" of 2003. Presentation with CD-rom "FDNY Emerging Technology and the FDNY" re: communications. Digital files/PDFs from Cengage Learning of Spadafora's Green Book, 2013. (Includes digital formats, video)
- Policies & Procedures. Education. Reference., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9854)
  Binder of course material for Command & General Staff, held in Tucson. Print matter re: Montana travel/visits and tearsheets, manuals, etc re: wildfires. Article by Spadafora on origin of FDNY incident management team/incident command system (IMT/ICS) with related print matter tie-in to wildfires. 2 CDs: FDNY Operations at bombings and explosions presentation (2004) and nuclear threat presentation (2004).(Includes digital formats)
- Policies & Procedures. Education. Reference., circa 1980s-1990s (Offsite-box 9860)
  Overstuffed binder labeled "Management": reading materials re: first line supervisory training (leadership, stress management, diversity/discrimination, etc.). Binder: [Fire] Company Administration Manual (procedures), 1990s. Binder: Command Chief Circulars, mid 1980s. "CBR flipbook" (laminated photos of biological, chemical, etc hazards and related).
- Policies & Procedures. Education. Specifics (social clubs)., circa 2000s (Offsite-box 9777)
  3 fire prevention textbooks with instructor guides. LPPA(?) binder with various fire dept memos/circulars and an ECB (Environmental Control Board) manual. Manual of fire inspection guides. Packet of miscellaneous documents and photos re social club fire prevention/violations.
- Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9427)
  Binder: "Company Officers Guide: To Line of Duty Deaths", 2009. Overstuffed binder labeled "CPR/CFR-D" (Certified First Responder-Defibrillation)": various directives from various medical offices, including EMS. Tearsheets and other matter. Binder: "TPR Manual" (Time & Payroll Report): procedures, articles re: timekeeping, system, time fraud, leaves, etc. Manual of Requisitions & Payroll. Print matter: tear sheets on "Technology" re: various aspects, including first response, drones, general.
- Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 2000s (Offsite-box 9746)
  Accordion folder: "Safety. Firefighter near miss reports." Bound: FDNY's "Operational Guide for Underground Subway Stations". Bound: Subway Education Day material. Thick file of ARCS (Communications) documents and CD. 1 book "City on Fire". (Includes digital formats)
- Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 2000s (Offsite-box 9781)
  A few miscellaneous documents re bombs and bomb threats. FDNY operational guides. A binder labeled "Fire" that is a preposterously overstuffed pile of articles, print matter and other reference material related to some aspect of fire prevention (e.g. construction techniques).
- Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 1985-2000s (Offsite-box 9782)
  Slides in carousel with index (appears to be related to permits and violations). Print matter: 1 WNYF (2004); Booklets: FDNY Administrative Medals & Awards (2005, 2007); Fire Prevention Violation Reference Guide (1986); Fire Prevention Inspector Hand-out (1985); Prevention Administrative Codes; textbook re fire inspection; book by Kerik. Universal Summons procedure guides and related docs. Standard Form of Orders (SFO) Guide and related NOV guide. 6 CDs (labeled as emails, back-up, desktop, PDFs/Powerpoint/Forcible Entry). 5 floppies (none labeled, probably blank). (Includes digital formats)
- Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 1960s-2007 (Offsite-box 9858)
  All print matter: FDNY Operational Reference (7th ed, 2007). About 20 books (1960s-90s) on arson, arson investigations, explosives. Copy of the Anarchist's Cookbook. FDNY draft emergency response plan for Improvised explosive devices (2005).
- Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 1997-2015 (Offsite-box 13866)
  Thick file labeled "CTDF" (counter-terrorism), includes tearsheets, booklets (including First Responders Bridge Guide with structural info on NYC bridges), publications, etc (especially "The Watchline" and Homeland Security notices) re bottle bombs, potential threats, etc. circa 1997-2015. Files on rooftop cooling tower inspections in connection with Legionnnaire's Disease. Some loose papers re pensions/medical. A few CDs with fire code chapters. (Includes digital formats)
- Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 1980s-2018 (Offsite-box 13868)
  2 binders of fire prevention directives, 1980s. FDNY Alteration, Construction & Demolition manuals, 2000s. FDNY RBIS (Risk Building Inspection System) User Manuals, 2012. International Fire Code book, 2018. Fire code pocket guide and print-outs. Various articles/tearsheets re: fires (batteries, tunnels, cranes). CD "Ice rink pic" and "LNG plants". CDs (about 30); most appear to be document downloads (fire code, building codes, training manuals on fire prevention, etc.); some personally created, including IGCC Powerpoint for NYS Fire Marshals, 2011. (Includes digital formats)
- Policies & Procedures. Specifics (social clubs). Reference., circa 1990s-2000s (Offsite-box 13867)
  Binder: FDNY Fire Prevention Manual, 1990s-2000s, with heavy inserts and annotations. Binder: Cabarets/Social Clubs LL (local law) 41 & 16 procedures, directives, etc. Files on public building inspections and procedures. Clippings and other print matter on factory, concert, etc fires. "Pyrotechnic Displays: a Guide for the Field."
- Policies & Procedures. Specifics. Education. Personal., circa 1996-2010 (Offsite-box 9802)
  5 binders: 1) "Battalion 4": Memos and other items distributed to Bat 4 (some specific to them, some general FDNY matters), 1996-99 (Spadafora is identified as Battalion Chief of #4 on a 1998 memo). 2) Various blank reporting forms, procedures, notices, late 1990s-circa 2000. 3) Labeled "Division 11" (Spadafora is Deputy Chief) includes blank reporting forms, lists of fire units in the city, FDNY telephone directory, and some procedures, circa 2000. 4) Also labeled "Division 11" includes memos and such for D11 (and D6 also), with some incident planning and exercises, late 1990s with some earlier and some to 2005. 5) Another labeled "Battalion 4" also with memos, etc as with binder 1. Folder labeled "Division 14" with various incident action plans (e.g. US Open 2008) and drills (e.g. NY and Atlantic RR disaster drill, 2003; Fort Totten drill, 2001), Management Appraisal, Reviews and Comparisons (MARC), for D14, 2001. NYFD Forcible Entry Guide, 2010.
- Policies & Procedures. Specifics. Education. Reference., circa 1996-2008 (Offsite-box 9803)
  Binder "Division 1" includes operational SOPs for 1996, with other earlier procedures, later incident drills and plans, and other documents. Folder labeled "calendars" but appears to be mostly blank forms with some administrative notes with one workchart calendar for 2002. Several other folders: Division 5, P (Permanent) Circulars; Division 15 (action plans, including for West Indian Day, 2003); WTC high rise fire exercise 1999; various action plans & drills; Division 13 Covering Officer Information Booklet; Division 6 documents; Vaal Train derailment hazardous materials overview 2009; Division 3 event plans including President George W. Bush visit 2005; fire reports 2000-01; overturned fuel truck in Queens 2008 (with CDs of FDNY photos and tanker fires Powerpoint presentation); miscellaneous small files on divisions 7, 8 and 13. Final scorecard for Manhattan Borough Command Strategic Plan 2007-08. A small case with a few photo slides of buildings. (Includes digital formats)
- Policies & Procedures. World Trade Center. Education. Personal., circa 1985-2002 (Offsite-box 9850)
  Binder: Strategy Tactics Operational Mapping Plan (STOMP), set of maps showing by various divisions of NYC the locations of fire units, subways, generators, NYPD precincts, EMS deployments and stations, and community board, etc., by Bureau of Ops, Planning & Strategy Unit/Phoenix Unit (2000s). FDNY annual reports 1985, 1987, 1988. Various print matter on technical subjects, but appear to be implicitly connected with WTC recovery: safety rigging course (2001); "Evacuation Safety" (2000), with insert re: WTC emergency project training announcement; Fed regulations on construction with Powerpoint presentation inserts on trenching/evacuations and OSHA; two binders of material on training for crane operations (with a "Crane Risk Management Report in re: WTC emergency clean-up" executive summary (Oct 11, 2001). FDNY specific: booklets of NYC firehouse locations prepared by Don Schmidt of Battalion 4; Massey Pre-Fire Plans in Service for New York, division 1 (34th street down to Battery), includes key info on certain buildings, including New York Stock Exchange, Empire State Building, Hotel Pennsylvania, and World Financial Center (Oct 2001). 2 books re: WTC/9/11. 2 binders of personal material: 1 of material mostly about the James Tonry Memorial 5K Run, a benefit for the NY Firefighters Burn Center (first three annual runs, 1995-97); and various documents related to Spadafora's time as captain of Ladder Company 150 (snapshots, admin procedures, checklists, company dinner publicity, etc.). Announcement of Tonry's death in 1994 (member of Co 150). 1993-1995. VHS: FDNY Promotion Ceremony, 8/29/02. Floppies. (Includes digital formats, video)
- Personal. Education., circa 1980s-1990s (Offsite-box 9768)
  About half the box relates to Spadafora's graduate studies at John Jay in mid-80s (notes, notebooks, syllabus, copies of reading material). About half relates to course in mid-1980s when Spadafora seems to be taking a Fire Science course. Much printed matter on investigations (e.g., "Fire & Arson Investigator" journals). Some material re: fire science course Spadafora taught.
- Personal. Education. Specifics (Cirque du Soleil), circa 1980s-2008 (Box OS-2)
  Laminated sign "Possible indicators of terrorist activity" (2). Laminated NYC "Communications Picture Board", 2000 (2). Laminated "evacuation map" for the Cirque du Soleil, 2008. 7 laminated maps of the "collapsed status" on various levels at WTC (Sept 27, 2001). Many copies of Spadafora's "Presentation of Qualifications" used in search for teaching position around 1990, and perhaps other purposes (I took one of the many copies for on-site reference). Several martial arts certificates. Martial arts photo album. Set of laminated "Tactical Training Tips" from the FDNY Bureau of Training for posting at Housewatch (2005). (Includes artifacts)
- Personal. Reference., circa 1970s-1980s (Offsite-box 9870)
  Spadafora's exam booklets from chemistry class at Queens (1975), notebook from criminal justice courses at CW Post (1978-79), notebooks from physics at John Jay (1985), workbooks from a first aid course (1970s?), Spadafora's paper (original with photos, and a photocopy) titled "Arson: the Problem, the Investigation, and Possible Solutions" for his Masters Degree at LIU/CW Post (1982). 2 packets of clippings, one labeled "criminal justice newspaper articles", the other unlabeled but also related to crime. Print matter: books/pamphlets on crime, criminal justice, arson, firearms. Artifacts: ear protectors in connection with firearms. 2 VHS videocassettes: "Learn Gun Safety with Eddie Eagle" and Goshin Club's "A Woman's Guide to Firearms." (Includes video, artifacts)
- Personal. Reference., circa 1980s-2010s (Offsite-box 9785)
  3 management textbooks and 2 on reading skills. Spadafora's desk notepad. Print matter "How to be successful on oral assessment exercises for police promotion." Parking violations pad with summons/defendants listed, circa 1984-89. Hazardous Material Mitigation Comparison material: reference materials, materials acquired from various fire depts globally, including Tokyo, floppies, etc: all this appears to be in relation to a project management course taken by Spadafora for the Fire Officers Management Institute. Firefighter benefits info (1981). 100 MB zip drive labeled with post-it "DAC Spadafora". Promotion to battalion chief course material (Spadafora taking it). Tutorial exercise "Rems" for taking deputy chief's test, 1988. (Includes digital formats)
- Personal. World Trade Center., circa 1970s-2018 (Box OS-3)
  WNYF posthumous compilation of Spadafora's published works. Photo of fire truck (Squad 1). Poster photo of Spadafora, Asst Chief Fire Prevention (possibly from memorial service?). Several rolled documents re: WTC. Banner re: Spadafora noting that he was the 178th to die, so likely part of a memorial service. Framed display of track medals. WTC photo. Oversize signed get-well displays. (Includes artifacts)
- Personal. World Trade Center. Reference., circa 1970s-2010s (Box OS-4)
  WTC photographs and images. Spadafora x-ray/MRIs of elbow and knee, 1995-2004. Prints (historic graphic works) of firefighters. Framed certificate and medal of 2012 FDNY Administrative award to team (including Spadafora) for information kiosk project, DiamondPlate Workgroup. BS diploma from John Jay (1986). MS diploma from LIU, CW post (1982). Resolution from NYC Loft Board honoring Spadafora, 2018. Ju jitsu list showing color belts earned for different moves. Reproduction with photo of Spadafora's probationary school training record (1978). A piece of the cladding used on the Grenfell Towers (which burned badly). A bag of rings, medals, pins, etc. Mobile phone. (Includes artifacts)
- Reference ("green book")., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 7434)